Star Health Insurance Company's name is
on everyone's lips these days. The reason is the massive
leak of their customer data.
This is not good news for such a large insurance company.
In today's Report Card video, we will review Star
Health & Allied Insurance Company in detail
for you.
Now, because Star Health is a
big name in the insurance industry,
what is the story behind it? How did this company
start? How did Star Health
Insurance Company's policies reach every household?
What plans can you avail from Star Health Insurance Company? What are the options available for you in this
company's health insurance plan bouquet?
We will also learn very important things about claims
in this video. Income Ratio and Claim
Settlement Ratio are very important
metrics. What do they reveal and indicate about this company,
which is
very important for us to know. We
will check the solvency margin, which is an indicator of Star Health's
financial health.
How can you file a claim with Star Health Insurance?
What is the method for filing a cashless claim? How many cashless network
hospitals do you have?  You will get a
reimbursement claim. How can you file it? Will
you face any problem in it? We are going to check all this in
detail in today's video.
After reviewing Star Health Insurance in detail, I will
also tell you what my opinion is about this company, that is,
what shortcomings I see in this company and what are the
specialties and good things of this company.
We will definitely discuss those too. So, if you are
looking for the best health insurance company in India, then you should definitely know about India's largest
stand-alone health insurance company, i.e.
Star Health. So, let's
not delay and quickly
start this video. Star Health
Insurance Company was started in 2006 by Mr.
Venkat Swami Jagannathan.
Star Health Insurance Company is headquartered in Chennai. At that time, there was
no awareness about health insurance at all
and doing business was also not as smooth as it is today.
But due to the teamwork of Star Health Insurance
and its large agent force,
today it has become India's largest stand-
alone health insurance company, that is, the
company which does business only in health insurance
and in this segment
i.e.
Star Health has a 45% market share in standalone health insurance,
meaning every second policy sold by standalone health insurance companies is from
Star Health Insurance.
In the overall health insurance industry,
it has a 15% market share, which is a significant
market share. To ensure the
smooth running of such a large insurance company,
Star Health has more than 850 branches across India,
employing over 15,000 employees.
Star Health Insurance's
more than 6.5 million
agents, who deliver
Star Health Insurance
policies and services to every corner of India, have played a significant role in its rise to this position.
Star Health Insurance's policies are
considered affordable, beautiful, and durable, and
using this factor,
Star Health Insurance has
established a strong foothold in smaller cities. In this next
segment, let's explore the health insurance plans
offered by Star Health Insurance.
Its first and latest plan
is the Star Health Insurance Superstar
Plan. This plan is quite innovative compared to Star Health Insurance's previous
plans.  It
's quite flexible, but
you won't find the option to port or migrate.
Star Health Insurance's best-
selling plan today is the Star Health Assure
Insurance Policy. This policy offers built-
in benefits like maternity and consumer benefits, meaning you'll get complete coverage. This makes it
Star Health Insurance
's best-selling plan. The Star
Health Comprehensive Plan is also a very good
plan and has been issued by
Star Health Insurance for quite some time. There's also the
Young
Star Plan, which
targets the below-40 age group. It includes
maternity benefits,
pre-exit illness coverage, and specific illnesses. There's only a one-year waiting period for pre-exit illnesses and specific
illnesses, making
it quite unique.
Star Health's next plan is Family
Health Optima FAO. Who hasn't
heard of it? FAO is the plan for which
Star Health
Insurance has sold the most policies to date. There was a time when
Star Health sold nothing but FAO.  It used to be
non-existent, but recently its
prices have been revised and have almost doubled.
So now most policy holders are
migrating or porting from this plan.
Providing good coverage to females,
Star Health Insurance has
also launched Women Care Plan, which specifically
covers female health-related issues. Along with this,
you will
also get plans for critical illness in Star Health.
You can also choose senior citizen plan, that is,
you can get a plan for the elderly person in your family.
Within Star Health, you get a
plan for them by the name of Red Carpet. If
you also want to take a personal accident policy, then
you will get the plan in Star on individual and family floater basis.
Apart from this, cancer care means that
policy holders
who are already diagnosed with cancer but do
not have any symptoms yet, they
can also take a cancer care plan. Apart from this,
if diabetes is a pre-existing disease, then they
can also take a separate plan and if
cardiac  If you already have a
stent or have heart-related
problems, you'll find a separate plan for them as well.
Looking at the list of plans offered by Star Health Insurance, it
appears that they have one of the most extensive
plans available in the industry,
meaning you have a wide range of options to
cater to different needs.
Suppose you've purchased a plan from Star Health Insurance,
but how does this company fare in terms of claims,
which is most often mentioned
in the comments and reviews. To
assess this, let's review some
crucial metrics related to claims. The
first metric is the claim settlement
ratio. Its definition is that if an
insurance company has 100 claims, the number of claims
resolved by it becomes the
company's claim settlement ratio.
Star Health Insurance's
CSR is 82, or 100 out of every
100 claims.  Star Health Insurance
cannot be said to have settled 82 claims. If we
look at the health insurance industry, the
number of claims, and the claim
settlement ratio, a
claim settlement ratio of at least 90 is
considered a healthy claim settlement ratio. However,
82 certainly cannot be considered good.
Star Health Insurance Company will have to work hard on this. The
next
important metric is the income ratio. This
ratio indicates
how much of the claims an insurance company has
disbursed back
to its policyholders for every ₹1 it collects by selling its policies. The income ratio of Star Health
Insurance is 65, but it falls in the ideal range.
If
a company has an income ratio between 55 and 75, it can be
considered ideal. This means that a company is neither
too lenient in paying claims
nor too strict, which means that it can be
called an unreasonable claim ratio.  Let's talk about
solvency margins. The
company will pay the claims, but if there are a large number of
claims in the future, it has enough money and the financial
strength to pay all the claims.
This is what the solvency margin tells us.
Star Health Insurance Company has a
solvency margin of two times, meaning it has
twice the amount of money it owes to the insured. According to
IRD regulations, the company should have one and a half
times this amount.
This is a very healthy solvency margin.
We also checked the rating report of Care Age, a credit rating agency.
This
credit rating agency has
given Star Health Insurance Company a rating of Triple A, meaning stable, meaning the insurance
company's financial position is sound.
Within this document, this rating agency has
also mentioned some strengths of the company,
including the comfortable solvency margin that
we just discussed. Along with this, there is
also mention of gradual improvement in profitability.
Some shortcomings have also been mentioned in the credit report. The
first shortcoming mentioned in this credit report  What has been said is that it
is a single line of business,
which means this insurance company does
not do any other work except health insurance, which
means there is
no diversity at all. If there is a loss in one business, then they do
not have any other product or business to compensate for it.
But apart from this, their investment
portfolio is quite strong.
Their
investment portfolio is worth Rs 14000 crore, out of which 34 percent of their
investments are in
government securities, which is one of the
safest investment instruments.
Apart from this, 64 percent of their investments are in
triple A rated corporate bonds,
both of which are government
securities and triple A rated corporate
bonds. Both these instruments are quite
safe and along with this, they
are also highly liquid, which means they can redeem their investments
quickly in case of
major claim happenings. Now the financial
position of Star Health Insurance Company
seems to be quite good, which means this
company has no shortage of money. Now
in the next segment, we will talk about the
claim process of Star Health Insurance, that is, you  If you
file a claim, let's explore your
experience.
First, let's talk about their cashless
network hospitals.
You have access to over 14,000 cashless networks across India, which is a large
network of hospitals. This provides
flexibility. You'll find more hospitals in your city
where you
can avail cashless treatment. This means that no
policyholder will have to pay any
money upfront, which is a
good thing. To avail cashless treatment,
in case of emergency, you must intimate the
insurance company within 24 hours of admission. You must
call their
toll-free number and inform them that
a patient has been admitted for this treatment.
Furthermore, if you are planning any treatment or
hospitalization,
you can obtain approval for your treatment two to three days before admission, ensuring
you do
n't face any inconvenience during treatment. The special thing is that
Star Health Insurance offers in-
house claim settlement, meaning there's
no TPA involvement in the
claim.  For approval, the hospital directly
uploads documents to Star Health Insurance, and
you receive approval or claim status directly from Star Health Insurance.
You won't face
claim delays or delays in claim status due to the lack of TP involvement.
Now, let's talk about reimbursement claims. If
you get treatment at a hospital that does
n't have a cashless tie-up with Star Health Insurance, or if
your claim is for pre- and
post-hospitalization, or if the
insurance company hasn't approved you for cashless
treatment at a network hospital,
then you'll need to
file a reimbursement claim. You can
collect all the claim documents, including claim forms, invoices, and prescriptions and reports, and submit them
to the nearest Star Health Insurance branch.
You can also courier the original documents to their address.
You can also enlist the help of your agent.
Can you process a claim by
uploading these documents online through your mobile app?
No, such an option is
not available with Star Health Insurance today.
You may find this facility available in the future,
but as of
October 2024, online remembrance
claims are not available with Star Health Insurance. A
list of the documents required for a reimbursement claim is currently visible on the screen. You will need to
collect these documents and
submit them to the insurance company. If you
wish, you can pause the video and
read this list to
understand the
documents you
may need for a reimbursement claim. Next comes the segment,
friends, about knowing the very important contact details related to Star Health Insurance.
If you are associated with Star Health
Insurance, are
thinking of purchasing a policy, have a
query, or have any claim-related conversation,
you may need these contact details
first.  The contact
details are their toll-free number where you
can call and resolve your query.
These are the two numbers that are currently
visible on the screen. The first number
is
18425 2255 and the second toll-free number is
180012 4477. If you want to get your views in writing or
want to get your queries answered, you
can also email Star Health Insurance. Their customer care email ID is
support@studentidentify.com. You
can check and read this email
ID. If you want
any written communication from the insurance company, then
this is the matter. Now that everything is
going well or we need to know the status
of a claim or a policy, we
can communicate this way. However, if you are
not happy with any of Star Health Insurance's services, the company's policy, the claim
process, or have any other complaint against
Star Health Insurance,
you can also complain to Star Health Insurance's
Grievances Department.
Where do you have to do this?  What are its benefits?
First, where should you lodge a complaint, and then
where should you escalate your matter?
I'm providing a link to the full details
in the description of this video. By
clicking on that link, you
can see complete information on how you can raise your issue with
Star Health Insurance's
grievance department.
Now, friends, after
learning so much about Star Health Insurance, it's time to
conclude the video. I'll
share my opinion on what I genuinely liked about Star Health Insurance
and what shortcomings I see in this company. So, let's
first
discuss the advantages. The first plus
point is that it offers a wide range of
policies. You have so
many policy options that
your needs will be met. You
can choose health insurance for yourself from its wide range of policies. The
second plus point is affordable prices.
You'll find Star Health Insurance's plans and policies to be
reasonable in price. Secondly,
you won't see the revision frequency increasing.  Now,
this seems to be happening based on past revisions,
but
I can't say what the future holds. However,
based on past data,
you'll see fewer revisions in Star Health's plans. The
third plus point is that
you'll find Star Health Insurance's presence
everywhere. When it comes to network hospitals,
they're the largest in the industry.
Branches are a huge
network of branches. You'll also find agents available
for help. If
you want agent-assisted purchasing,
you'll easily find Star Health insurance agents. The
connectivity and
presence of their network are easily
accessible, and you
can avail of their policies and services from anywhere. Now, let's talk about
some of the shortcomings of Star Health Insurance that
I see. The
first one I'd mention is that
companies should take safety measures to prevent
such mistakes.
Infiltrations that lead to data leaks or
customer information leaks are
completely intolerable. This ca
n't happen now.  Because of this data, who
knows what losses policyholders may have to bear?
Who will be responsible for it
and who will decide the responsibility for this? Now, to ensure that
such negligence does not happen in the future, the
insurance company must
take necessary steps. The second shortcoming I
see is outdated tech.
Star Health Insurance's tech-based
services, whether it's their mobile app,
agent app, or their online portal, are a bit
outdated. I think
other insurance companies' apps,
websites, or the
options there, or their
speed, are quite good.
When you open Star Health Insurance's mobile app, you'll notice the
logo as soon as
it starts processing. You'll
realize that it's a bit outdated.
Nowadays, it's the era of AI.
Understanding this, insurance companies should
work on their technology so that
customers get a good experience. The
next shortcoming I see is
their number of complaints. If we
look at the industry average, every  10,000
claim plates are filed, but the
average of complaints filed by Star
also exceeds this and goes up to 29, that
is, 29 complaints are filed for every 10,000 claims.
I did not see any strong grievance vertical for this. It takes a lot of time to get a response. So, firstly,
how should these complaints be resolved? They should be resolved
timely. For this, they should have a good
grievance vertical
because you will not grow just by increasing the number of policies and market share.
For this, it is also important that your customers get good service and
their happiness. Because
every person invests their hard-earned money in health insurance
and if they do not get the service on time, then there is nothing
worse for them than this.
That time is of medical emergency. So, there should be
timely resolution of claim plates,
for which they should create a sound
and strong grievance vertical. So,
friends, today's report
In this video of the card, you have understood
every important aspect about Star Health Insurance.
I
also told you my opinion about it. Now this video
will help you a lot while choosing a good health insurance
policy and a good health insurance
company. If you
want to give advice about how you liked this video, then
you can also tell us by commenting
and to give your love and support, do
like and share the video. If you want to see similar
important videos and
reviews of other companies of the Report Card series, then do
subscribe to the channel.
I, Harvinder Singh, now take your permission. I will get your
permission in the next video. Till then,
take care of yourself, stay happy
and stay healthy. Jai Hind.